A Guide to the Records of Western State Hospital, 1825-2000
Library of Virginia
- Series V. Report Books and Other Registers, 1847-1988., Extent: .7 cubic feet of records and 605 volumes.
  - Series V., Subseries L. Ward Reports, 1866-1947.
    - Monthly Report Books, 1866-1947.
      Restricted: Report books containing patient names and information that are less than 125 years old. Please see reference staff if you wish to view a register that has a date range that encompasses both unrestricted and restricted content. Contains volumes that document monthly statistical information about patients at Western State Hospital. The earliest volumes are set up in grids that show when a patient did housework, outside work, sewing, laundry, went to chapel, and walked outside. These ledgers also note when seizures or "fits" took place, and the use of restraints. Transfers, furloughs, elopements, discharges and deaths are also included in these reports. Each day the activities of each patient are accounted for with letters or symbols that apply to each type of activity. Definitions of the letters and symbols are usually located at either the front or back of each ledger. In some of the ledgers, monthly accounts and descriptions of each female patient's catamenial (menstrual) period are recorded, usually at the back of the volume. The recordkeeping technique changes in the later monthly reports, where some registers were given the title of "roll." After approximately 1910, while each patient on the ward is still listed, the entries only note transfers, furloughs, discharges, elopements and deaths. The volumes no longer track other patient activities. Additionally, patient weight registers can be found at the back of several later volumes. Researchers should also cross-reference the weight ledgers in Series IV. Patient Records, Subseries G. Medical Records. The monthly report ledgers were maintained for individual wards, ward assignments are noted in the content list. At the end of the list for the male department are two "Records of Monthly Reports" that compile all of the statistical data found in the monthly reports. The number of admissions, deaths, discharges, and average number of patients in the hospital are tallied for each month. The records also specify the number of patients in each ward. The monthly report books are part of accessions 41404 and 41253.
      - Male Patients.
        - 1872-1875 (Ward 6). (Volume 908)
        - 1877-1879 (Ward 7). (Volume 909)
        - 1880-1883 (Ward 5). (Volume 910)
        - 1880-1884 (Ward 4). (Volume 911)
        - 1880-1884 (Ward 6). (Volume 912)
        - 1880-1884 (Ward 7). (Volume 913)
        - 1880-1888 (Ward 3). (Volume 914)
        - 1882-1887 (Ward 9). (Volume 915)
        - 1883-1888 (Ward 10). (Volume 916)
        - 1884-1889 (Ward 4). (Volume 917)
        - 1884-1889 (Ward 5). (Volume 918)
        - 1884-1889 (Ward 6). (Volume 919)
        - 1886-1891 (Ward 8). (Volume 920)
        - 1888-1893 (Ward 10). (Volume 921)
        - 1889-1894 (Ward 4). (Volume 922)
        - 1889-1894 (Ward 6). (Volume 923)
        - 1895-1904 (Ward 6). (Volume 924)
        - 1899-1909 (Ward 3). (Volume 925)
        - 1904-1908 (Ward 6). (Volume 926)
        - 1905-1909 (Ward 7). (Volume 927)
        - 1909-1911 (Ward 6). (Volume 928)
        - 1909-1916 (possibly Ward 7). (Volume 929)
        - 1911-1917 (possibly Ward 6). (Volume 930)
        - 1916-1920 (possibly Ward 7). (Volume 931)
        - 1917-1921 (Ward 6). (Volume 932)
        - 1920-1923 (possibly Ward 7). (Volume 933)
        - 1921-1925 (Ward 6). (Volume 934)
        - 1923-1926 (Ward 7). (Volume 935)
        - 1925-1927 (Ward 6). (Volume 936)
        - 1926-1928 (Ward 7). (Volume 937)
        - 1927-1930 (Ward 6). (Volume 938)
        - 1928-1930 (Ward 7). (Volume 939)
        - 1930-1932 (Ward 7). (Volume 940)
        - 1930-1932 (Ward 7). (Volume 941)
        - 1932-1934 (Ward 7). (Volume 942)
        - 1932-1935 (Ward 6). (Volume 943)
        - 1935-1937 (Ward 6). (Volume 944)
        - 1935-1937 (Ward 7). (Volume 945)
        - 1935-1940 (Ward 14) [Also contains a patient weight register, 1942-1948]. (Volume 946)
        - 1937-1938 (Ward 8) [Also contains a patient weight register, 1942-1943]. (Volume 947)
        - 1937-1940 (possibly Ward 6). (Volume 948)
        - 1937-1940 (Ward 9) [Also contains a patient weight register, 1942-1947]. (Volume 949)
        - 1938-1940 (Ward 12) [Also contains a patient weight register, 1941-1948]. (Volume 950)
        - 1939-1940 (Ward 4) [Also contains a patient weight register, 1942-1948]. (Volume 951)
        - 1939-1940 (Ward 7) [Also contains a patient weight register, 1941-1948]. (Volume 952)
        - 1939-1940 (Ward 17) [Also contains a patient weight register, 1941-1948]. (Volume 953)
        - 1940 (Ward 13) [Also contains a patient weight register, 1940-1947]. (Volume 954)
        - Record of Monthly Reports (all wards), 1895-1925. (Volume 955)
        - Record of Monthly Reports (all wards), 1925-1941. (Volume 956)
      - Female Patients.
        - 1866-1867 (1st Floor). (Box 229, Folder 1)
        - 1866-1867 (2nd Floor). (Box 229, Folder 2)
        - 1866-1867 (3rd Floor). (Box 229, Folder 3)
        - 1866-1867 (R Wing). (Box 229, Folder 4)
        - 1867-1869 (1st Floor). (Volume 957)
        - 1867-1869 (2nd Floor). (Volume 958)
        - 1870-1873 (Ward E). (Volume 959)
        - 1870-1874 (Ward F). (Volume 960)
        - 1874-1878 (Ward E). (Volume 961)
        - 1875-1880 (Ward D). (Volume 962)
        - 1880-1884 (Ward D). (Volume 963)
        - 1880-1884 (Ward F). (Volume 964)
        - 1880-1884 (Ward G). (Volume 965)
        - 1880-1884 (Ward H). (Volume 966)
        - 1880-1884 (Ward I). (Volume 967)
        - 1880-1885 (Ward A). (Volume 968)
        - 1880-1885 (Ward C). (Volume 969)
        - 1880-1885 (Ward K). (Volume 970)
        - 1884-1889 (Ward D). (Volume 971)
        - 1884-1889 (Ward E). (Volume 972)
        - 1884-1889 (Ward F). (Volume 973)
        - 1884-1889 (Ward G). (Volume 974)
        - 1884-1889 (Ward H). (Volume 975)
        - 1884-1889 (Ward I). (Volume 976)
        - 1886-1890 (Ward C). (Volume 977)
        - 1886-1890 (Ward K). (Volume 978)
        - 1886-1890 (Ward L). (Volume 979)
        - 1895-1905 (Ward K). (Volume 980)
        - 1896-1905 (Ward C). (Volume 981)
        - 1911-1918 (possibly Ward C). (Volume 982)
        - 1937-1941 (Ward M) [Also contains a patient weight register, 1941]. (Volume 983)
        - 1941-1946 (Ward M) [Also contains a patient weight register, 1942-1946]. (Volume 984)
        - 1942-1947 (Ward C). (Volume 985)
    - Weekly Reports, 1866-1945.
      Restricted: Report books containing patient names and information that are less than 125 years old. Please see reference staff if you wish to view a register that has a date range that encompasses both unrestricted and restricted content. Contains weekly reports with information about each ward including the capacity, actual number patients, and the number of patients taking medicine or on a special diet. The ledgers also leave room to note where or how the patients were employed at the hospital, any special activities in which they participated, or if there were any incidents or accidents. The ledgers also have notes about specific patients in terms of admissions, furloughs, transfers, elopements and deaths. Several weekly report volumes listed at the end of the female patient section are not quite the same as the others, though they were also made on a weekly basis. They were included here due to the method of recording and the type of information recorded, despite the fact that they do not fit into the general chronology.
      Arranged first according to patient sex, and then chronologically within.
      - Male and Female Patients.
        - 1866-1870. (Volume 986)
      - Male Patients.
        - 1889-1891. (Volume 987)
        - 1891-1894. (Volume 988)
        - 1894-1898. (Volume 989)
        - 1898-1902. (Volume 990)
        - 1902-1905. (Volume 991)
        - 1905-1909. (Volume 992)
        - 1909-1911. (Volume 993)
        - 1912-1914. (Volume 994)
        - 1914-1917. (Volume 995)
        - 1917-1921. (Volume 996)
        - 1921-1926. (Volume 997)
        - 1926-1931. (Volume 998)
        - 1931-1937. (Volume 999)
        - 1937-1941. (Volume 1000)
        - 1941-1943. (Volume 1001)
      - Female Patients.
        - 1883-1884. (Volume 1002)
        - 1892-1896. (Volume 1003)
        - 1908-1912. (Volume 1004)
        - 1912-1915. (Volume 1005)
        - 1915-1919. (Volume 1006)
        - 1919-1923. (Volume 1007)
        - 1923-1926. (Volume 1008)
        - 1926-1929. (Volume 1009)
        - 1932. (Volume 1010)
        - Miscellaneous Weekly Report Book, 1908-1910. (Volume 1011)
        - Miscellaneous Weekly Report Book, 1916-1920. (Volume 1023)
        - Miscellaneous Weekly Report Book, 1920-1923. (Volume 1012)
        - Miscellaneous Weekly Report Book, 1923-1927. (Volume 1024)
        - Miscellaneous Weekly Report Book, 1927-1932. (Volume 1025)
        - Miscellaneous Weekly Report Book, 1932-1935. (Volume 1026)
        - Miscellaneous Weekly Report Book, 1943-1945. (Volume 1027)
  - Series V., Subseries M. Wash Lists, 1887-1888.
    Contains laundry lists for all the female wards. The lists were compiled weekly for each individual ward. The lists noted how many of each piece of clothing or bed linen was to be washed for that ward. The wash list is part of accession 41404.
    - 1887-1888. (Volume 1013)
  - Series V., Subseries N. Visitor Registers, 1847-1878.
    Contains records of all outside visitors to Western State Hospital. Each entry includes the name of the visitor, the date, and their place of residence. The visitor registers are part of accession 41404.
    - 1847-1854. (Volume 1014)
    - 1854-1857. (Volume 1015)
    - 1857-1861. (Volume 1016)
    - 1861-1870. (Volume 1017)
    - 1870-1873. (Volume 1018)
    - 1876-1878. (Volume 1019)
- Series VI. Records Found at Eastern State Hospital, 1825-1918., Extent: 2 cu. ft.
  Contains correspondence, contracts, agreements, buildings and grounds records and other miscellaneous documents found during a records transfer at Eastern State Hospital in Williamsburg, Virginia in February 2010. According to records at Eastern State and Western State, the documents were removed from the Western State archives in 1983 and used by researchers to accurately reconstruct the Public Hospital at Colonial Williamsburg. The records were never returned to Western State and were eventually found in a basement at Eastern State in 1987. The records were taken to the Eastern State archives where they were housed until Eastern State transferred its historical records to the Library of Virginia. The records remain part of Eastern State Hospital accession 44812.
  Files are split into three categories: correspondence, subject files, and volumes. Most of the records in this series pertain to buildings, construction projects, contracting for supplies and labor, and basic hospital operations.
  - Series VI., Subseries A. Correspondence, 1835-1918.
    Contains varied superintendent's correspondence. Some of the letters are from friends and family inquiring about patients, while many of them pertain to Dr. Francis Stribling's outside professional affiliations. The correspondence includes folders of letters to and from Dr. Thomas S. Kirkbride of the Pennsylvania Hospital for the Insane and Dr. John M. Galt of Eastern Lunatic Asylum.
    Arranged chronologically by year.
    - 1835-1837. (Box 230, Folder 1)
    - 1841. (Box 230, Folder 2)
    - 1842. (Box 230, Folder 3)
    - 1843. (Box 230, Folder 4)
    - 1844. (Box 230, Folder 5)
    - 1845. (Box 230, Folder 6)
    - 1846. (Box 230, Folder 7)
    - 1847. (Box 230, Folder 8)
    - 1848-1849. (Box 230, Folder 9)
    - 1850. (Box 230, Folder 10)
    - 1851-1854. (Box 230, Folder 11)
    - 1855. (Box 230, Folder 12)
    - 1856-1857. (Box 230, Folder 13)
    - 1858-1859. (Box 230, Folder 14)
    - 1860. (Box 230, Folder 15)
    - 1866-1869. (Box 230, Folder 16)
    - 1870-1873. (Box 230, Folder 17)
    - 1874-1918. (Box 230, Folder 18)
    - undated. (Box 230, Folder 19)
    - Dr. John M. Galt, Eastern Lunatic Asylum, 1843-1857. (Box 230, Folder 20)
    - Dr. Thomas S. Kirkbride, Pennsylvania Hospital for the Insane, 1843-1873. (Box 230, Folder 21)
  - Series VI., Subseries B. Subject Files, 1825-1873.
    Contains a variety of files pertaining to various aspects of hospital operations, much of which is devoted to construction projects. The "Buildings and construction" folders contain specifications, contracts, proposals, and receipts for early construction projects at the hospital such as the building of walls, additions, and porticos, plastering, and painting. Other files contain contracts for the procurement of wood, meat, leather, and sundry goods. Two documents refering to slaves are also included, as are sporadic physician's reports and committee documents, and the commitment papers for the hospital's first patient, Anderson Kendall.
    Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
    - Annual reports, 1837-1838. (Box 230, Folder 22)
    - Application for admission, M.W. Vaughan, 1857. (Box 230, Folder 23)
    - Auditor's report, 1873. (Box 230, Folder 24)
    - Baker, Agreements regarding the, 1846-1855. (Box 230, Folder 25)
    - Beehive contract, 1856. (Box 230, Folder 26)
    - Blacksmith contract, 1866. (Box 230, Folder 27)
    - Buildings and construction, 1825-1826. (Box 230, Folder 28)
    - Buildings and construction, 1828-1831. (Box 230, Folder 29)
    - Buildings and construction, 1833-1835. (Box 230, Folder 30)
    - Buildings and construction, 1838. (Box 230, Folder 31)
    - Buildings and construction, 1840. (Box 230, Folder 32)
    - Buildings and construction, 1841-1842. (Box 231, Folder 1)
    - Buildings and construction, 1843-1844. (Box 231, Folder 2)
    - Buildings and construction, 1845-1847. (Box 231, Folder 3)
    - Buildings and construction, 1848-1855. (Box 231, Folder 4)
    - Buildings and construction, 1856-1859. (Box 231, Folder 5)
    - Buildings and construction, 1860-1864. (Box 231, Folder 6)
    - Buildings and construction, 1866-1873. (Box 231, Folder 7)
    - Buildings and construction, undated. (Box 231, Folder 8)
    - Report of the Committee (hiring a full-time physician), 1838. (Box 231, Folder 9)
    - Commitment papers, Anderson Kendall, 1828. (Box 231, Folder 10)
    - Contract documents, miscellaneous, 1837-1867; undated. (Box 231, Folder 11)
    - Document XIV. Letter from John M. Galt, M.D. Superintendent of the Eastern Lunatic Asylum, upon the Subject of the Site of a Lunatic Asylum, undated. (Box 231, Folder 12)
    - Document L. Report of the Investigating Committee of the Western Lunatic Asylum (with deposition), 1851-1852. (Box 231, Folder 13)
    - Furniture, Purchase of, 1843-1849; undated. (Box 231, Folder 14)
    - Gardening and landscaping, 1846-1870. (Box 231, Folder 15)
    - Gas works, 1855-1861; undated. (Box 231, Folder 16)
    - Indenture of Thomas Clary, 1852. (Box 231, Folder 17)
    - Instructions for male attendants (from the Superintendent), undated. (Box 231, Folder 18)
    - Land and property transfers, 1825-1873; undated. (Box 231, Folder 19)
    - Meat and butchering, 1831-1869. (Box 231, Folder 20)
    - Medicine, Purchase of, 1855-1871. (Box 231, Folder 21)
    - Petition to the Board of Directors (termination of support), 1873. (Box 231, Folder 22)
    - Physician's reports, 1836-1838. (Box 231, Folder 23)
    - Specifications of the Proposed Addition to the Northern Building of the Western Asylum, 1850. (Box 231, Folder 24)
    - Specifications Relative to the Enlargement of the South Additional Building of the Western Asylum, 1849. (Box 231, Folder 25)
    - Stribling Springs, 1859; 1870. (Box 231, Folder 26)
    - Sundry articles and goods, Purchase of, 1838-1872; undated. (Box 231, Folder 27)
    - Tanning and leather, 1868-1869. (Box 231, Folder 28)
    - Valuation and sale of slaves, 1852; 1857. (Box 231, Folder 29)
    - Water and water works, 1834-1857. (Box 231, Folder 30)
    - Wood, Purchase of, 1862-1863. (Box 231, Folder 31)
  - Series VI., Subseries C. Volumes, 1856-1859.
    Includes a workbook kept by building superintendent Thomas R. Blackburn that contains watercolor drawings of buildings, a bath, a steam boiler, and a laundry room. The book also contains detailed information and specifications for the construction of new additions, the heating system, gas works, and water supply, as well as accounting information such as receipts, payments, and stock lists.
    - Building superintendent's workbook (Thomas R. Blackburn), 1856-1859. (Volume 1022)
- Series VII. DeJarnette Sanatorium Admission Registers (Acc. 50989), 1932-1996., Extent: 3 volumes.
  Contains admissions registers, 1932-1996, of the DeJarnette State Sanatorium, also known as DeJarnette Center for Human Development. The registers typically contain the name of the patient, their patient number, their commitment status, the locality from which they came, and their diagnosis.
  - Admission register, 1932-1950. (Volume 1)
  - Admission register, 1950-1965. (Volume 2)
  - Admission register, 1965-1966. (Volume 3)
- Series VIII. Sterilization records and files of Dr. Jeffreys, 1927-1991., Extent: 1.05 cubic feet (3 boxes) and 3 volumes..
  Restricted: Admission records and sterilization records that are less than 125 years old. No viewing, photocopying, or redaction of medical records less than 125 years of age is allowed. This series includes sterilizations approved, sterilizations performed, sterilization patient records, an admission register, and files collected by Dr. A. W. Jeffreys, Jr., which include correspondence, reports, photographs, theses, and a scrapbook. This collection of Western State Hospital records was transferred separately in 2022.
  Sterilizations approved and performed consist of photocopied lists of patient names and include patients from Central State Hospital, Eastern State Hospital, Southwestern State Hospital, Lynchburg State Colony and Petersburg State Colonly, as well as Western State Hospital. These records are arranged chronologically. (RESTRICTED)
  Sterilization admission records are arranged include copies of commitment papers, medical records, and correspondence. (RESTRICTED)
  Sterilization record information forms are arranged alphabetically and include patient name and number, date of sterilization and death/discharged/transferred date. Many of the records include an attached copy of the master patient index card, though many are faded and illegible. (RESTRICTED). For additional sterilization records see Series IV, Subseries G, Medical Records.
  Admission register, 1928-1968, includes patient name and number, admission date, occupation, gender, age, residence, cause for admission, duration of symptoms before admission, physical description, time of residence in hospital, whether cured/much improved/improved/unimproved and whether removed/eloped/died, and remarks (RESTRICTED). This appears to be a duplicate of the admission register found in Series IV, Subseries A, Admission Records.
  Dr. A.W. (Alois Waldo) Jeffreys, Jr. (1923-1992) served as Chief Clinical Psycholigist at Western State Hospital for 33 years. His files include a small amount of correspondence, several reports and photographs of Dr. Jeffreys and other WSH staff members (Marie Beck, Lou Garber, Penelope Lewis, and Ann Moss) as well as a photograph of a portrait of Dr. Stribling. His papers also include two copies of a thesis - The Era of Moral Therapy at Western State Hospital by Nancy Feys Dunne, 1968; a scrapbook of clippings and other ephemera, 1959; and volume of Transorbital Lobotomies (1950-1956), created by Dr. Jeffreys in 1991 to document his work in this area. The Transorbital Lobotomies volumed includes copies of correspondence, patient records and photographs and is RESTRICTED.
  - Sterilizations approved, 1927-1930. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Sterilizations approved, 1937-1939. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Sterilizations approved, 1940-1949. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Sterilizations approved, 1950-1959. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Sterilizations approved, 1960-1964. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Sterilizations performed, 1937-1939. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Sterilizations performed, 1940-1949. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Sterilizations performed, 1950-1959. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Sterilizations performed, 1960-1963. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Sterilizations - Individual addmission record, 1930 Oct 18. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Sterilizations - Individual addmission record, 1932 Apr 13. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Sterilizations - Individual addmission record, 1936 Dec 6. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Sterilizations - Individual addmission record, 1937 May 12. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Sterilizations - Individual addmission record, 1938 Apr 10. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Orders appointing guardian for sterilization proceedings, 1966. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Sterilization record information - A, 1942-1980. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Sterilization record information - B, 1942-1980. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Sterilization record information - C, 1942-1980. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Sterilization record information - D, 1942-1980. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Sterilization record information - E, 1942-1980. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Sterilization record information - F, 1942-1980. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Sterilization record information - G, 1942-1980. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Sterilization record information - H, 1942-1980. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Sterilization record information - J, 1942-1980. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Sterilization record information - K, 1942-1980. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Sterilization record information - L, 1942-1980. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Sterilization record information - M, 1942-1980. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Sterilization record information - P, 1942-1980. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Sterilization record information - R, 1942-1980. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Sterilization record information - S, 1942-1980. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Sterilization record information - T, 1942-1980. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Sterilization record information - W, 1942-1980. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Sterilization procedures and forms (blank), 1952-1981. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Dr. Jeffreys: Correspondence, 1977-1985. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Dr. Jeffreys: Dedication of Staff Development Building named in honor of Dr. A. W. Jeffreys, Jr., 1991. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Dr. Jeffreys: Investigation on conditions at Western State Hospital (Report), 1981. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Dr. Jeffreys: Newspaper clipping - Breeding, undated. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Dr. Jeffreys: Photographs, 1956-1961. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Dr. Jeffreys: Some Facts About Western State Hospital (publication), 1965. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Dr. Jeffreys: Western State Hospital site map, 1973. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Dr. Jeffreys: Thesis (copy 1), 1968. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Dr. Jeffreys: Thesis (copy 2), 1968. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Transorbital Lobotomies (1950-1956), 1991. (Volume 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1959. (Volume 2)
  - Admission register, 1828-1868. (Volume 3)